Arno A. Penzias Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Arno A. Penzias Papers 1931-2006 1963-1998
MSS85338
Penzias, Arno A.
9,500 items
27 containers plus 2 oversize and 1 artifact
10.8 linear feet
1,006 digital files (442.70 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Scientist, corporate executive, and author. Correspondence, drafts of books, articles, and speeches, interviews, scientific articles, photographs, topical files, printed matter, digital files, and miscellaneous material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alpher, Ralph, 1921-2007--Correspondence.; Ash, E. A.--Correspondence.; Block, David L.--Correspondence.; Dicke, Robert H. (Robert Henry)--Correspondence.; Encrenaz, Pierre J.--Correspondence.; Fleury, Paul A.--Correspondence.; Gamow, George, 1904-1968--Correspondence.; Gazalé, Midhat J., 1929- --Correspondence.; Gilder, George F., 1939- --Correspondence.; Herman, Robert, 1914- --Correspondence.; Inose, Hiroshi, 1927- --Correspondence.; Julesz, Bela--Correspondence.; Morrison, Philip--Correspondence.; Nachtigall, Dieter, 1927- --Correspondence.; Peebles, P. J. E. (Phillip James Edwin)--Correspondence.; Penzias, Arno A.; Queisser, Hans J., 1931- --Correspondence.; Radner, Roy, 1927- --Correspondence.; Shoji, Masakazu, 1936- --Correspondence.; Spitzer, Lyman, 1914-1997--Correspondence.; Stibitz, George R. (George Robert), 1904-1995--Correspondence.; Townes, Charles H.--Correspondence.; Uenohara, Michiyuki, 1925-2007--Correspondence.; Weinberg, Steven, 1933- --Correspondence.; Wilson, Robert Woodrow, 1936-
Organizations
Bell Telephone Laboratories.; Lucent Technologies (Firm); New Enterprise Associates.
Subjects
Astrophysics.; Big bang theory.; Cosmic background radiation.; Cosmology.; Deuterium.
Occupations
Astrophysicists.; Authors.; Executives.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Arno A. Penzias, scientist, corporate executive, author, and venture capitalist, were given to the Library of Congress by Penzias in 2006.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some audiocassettes and videotapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. A drawing has been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Arno A. Penzias Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Arno A. Penzias are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the Arno A. Penzias Papers. Reference copies were created from the original digital media. Advanced notice is required to access the digital content; Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Online Content
A “Chart record,” Horn Antenna, Holmdel, N.J., 1964, is available on the Library of Congress Web site at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000123.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1933, April 26 Born, Munich, Germany
1939 Fled with family from Germany to England
1940 Immigrated to the United States with his family and settled in New York, N.Y.
1946 Became a naturalized citizen of the United States
1954 B.S., College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y. Married Anne Pearl Barras. Divorced 1996.
1954 1956 Radar officer, Army Signal Corps
1956 1958 Research assistant, Columbia Radiation Laboratory, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1958 M.A., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1961 Started thirty-seven year career at Bell Laboratories and its successor Lucent Technologies
1962 Ph.D. in physics, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1964 Discovered with Robert W. Wilson uniform microwave radiation emanating from all directions in the universe, documenting the Big Bang theory of the origin of the universe
1972 1976 Director, Radio Research Laboratories, Bell Laboratories
1978 Awarded with Robert W. Wilson the Nobel Prize for Physics
1981 1995 Vice president for research, Bell Laboratories and Lucent Technologies
1989 Published Ideas and Information: Managing in a High-Tech World. New York: Norton
1995 Published Harmony: Business, Technology & Life after Paperwork. New York: HarperBusiness
1995 1998 Vice president and chief scientist, AT &T Bell Laboratories and Lucent Technologies, Bell Laboratories Innovations
1996 Married Sherry Levit
1998 Venture partner, New Enterprise Associates
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Arno Allan Penzias (1933- ) span 1931-2006, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1963 to 1998. Penzias enjoyed a thirty-seven year career with Bell Laboratories and its successor Lucent Technologies, serving these organizations as an astrophysicist and eventually as chief scientist and vice president directing the corporate laboratory’s research and product development. Penzias with his colleague Robert Woodrow Wilson discovered a uniform microwave radiation emanating from beyond our galaxy the charting of which documented the Big Bang theory of the origins of the universe. For this achievement Penzias and Wilson shared a Nobel Prize for Physics in 1978.
Most of the collection is in English but includes material in German, Chinese, French, Swedish, Japanese, Spanish, Portugese, Italian, and Russian. The papers are organized into six series: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Oversize, Artifact, and Digital Files.
The General Correspondence contains letters exchanged with colleagues and friends including David Block, Paul A. Fleury, George Gamow, Hiroshi Inose, Roy Radner, and Charles H. Townes.
The Speeches and Writings include files on Penzias’s two books about information technology, Ideas and Information: Managing in a High-Tech World and Harmony: Business, Technology & Life after Paperwork, published in 1989 and 1995 respectively. Correspondence relating to the books is extensive and correspondents include E. A. Ash, Pierre J. Encrenaz, Midhat J. Gazalé, George F. Gilder, Hiroshi Inose, Bela Julesz, Philip Morrison, Dieter Nachtigall, Hans J. Queisser, Masakazu Shoji, Lyman Spitzer, George R. Stibitz, and Michiyuki Uenohara.
Penzias took on his duties directing Bell Laboratories in 1981, the year its parent company, AT & T, was ordered by court order to divest. The Subject File documents Penzias’s leadership during the period when Bell Laboratories became Lucent Technologies. It also sheds light on his earlier research career, such as his discovery of the cosmic background radiation for which he won the Nobel Prize, and his work on another indicator of a Big Bang, the abundance in the universe of deuterium, a stable isotope of hydrogen. A file relating to Penzias’s work on the origin of the elements includes correspondence with Big Bang theorists Ralph Alpher, Robert H. Dicke, Robert Herman (1914), P. J. E. Peebles, and Steven Weinberg (1933). Documentation obtained from Bell Laboratory’s Horn Antenna, with which Penzias and Wilson made their discovery on Crawford Hill in Holmdel, New Jersey, is available in photographs and a rolled, scroll-like “chart record” dating from 1964.
The Digital Files document Penzias's career as a venture capital partner with New Enterprises Associates after his retirement from Lucent Technologies and also include personal correspondence, family photographs and biographical material.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
General Correspondence, 1963-2002
Speeches and Writings, 1947-2005
Subject File, 1931-1998
Oversize, 1978-1983
Artifact, 1964
Digital Files, 1997-2006
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1963-2002 (Box 1)
  Correspondence with friends and colleagues with attached material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1963-2002, (6 folders) (Box 1)
- Speeches and Writings, 1947-2005 (Box 1-19)
  Drafts of books, articles, and speeches; interviews; poems; correspondence; background information; research files; and promotional and miscellaneous material..
  Arranged alphabetically by format, title, or type of material and therein chronologically or sequentially
  - Articles See also Containers 23-25, Science file (Box 1)
    - By Penzias (Box 1)
      - "2020," 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
        - Drafts (Box 1)
          - 1989-1993 (Box 1)
          - Undated (Box 2)
        - Published versions, 1971-1991, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous authors (Box 2)
      - 1948, 1965-1981, (4 folders) (Box 2)
      - 1982-1993, (7 folders) (Box 3)
      - 1994-2005, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Books (Box 4)
    - Harmony: Business, Technology & Life after Paperwork (Box 4)
      - Background information, 1981, 1991-1995 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1993-1995, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Drafts (Box 5)
        - No.1, chapters 1-10, 1994, (6 folders) (Box 5)
        - No. 2 (Box 5)
          - Introduction, dedication, and table of contents, 1994 (Box 5)
          - Chapters 1-7, 1994, (7 folders) (Box 6)
          - Chapters 8-10, (3 folders) (Box 7)
        - Copyediting, 1994 (Box 7)
        - Miscellany, 1994, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - Publication and promotion (Box 8)
        - Miscellany, 1993-1995 (Box 8)
        - Packets, 1995 (Box 8)
        - Reviews, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Ideas and Information: Managing in a High-Tech World (Box 8)
      - Background information (Box 8)
        - Miscellany, 1982-1990, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
        - Vail, Theodore N., undated (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
        - 1978, 1985-1988, (3 folders) (Box 9)
        - 1989 (Box 9)
          - Jan.-Oct., (6 folders) (Box 9)
          - Nov.-Dec. (Box 10)
        - 1990-1994 (Box 10)
      - Drafts (Box 10)
        - No. 1, chapters 1-9, 1987, (3 folders) (Box 10)
        - No. 2, undated (Box 10)
          - Chapters 1-6 (2 folders) (Box 10)
          - Chapters 7-9 (Box 11)
        - No. 3, meeting with editor, chapters 1-4, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 11)
        - No. 4 (Box 11)
          - Acknowledgment, preface, introduction, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 11)
          - Background information, 1986-1987 (Box 11)
          - Chapters (Box 11)
            - No. 1, 1987 (Box 11)
            - No. 2 (Box 11)
              - Background information, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
              - Text, 1987 (Box 11)
            - No. 3 (Box 11)
              - Background information, 1985-1988 (Box 11)
              - Text, 1987 (Box 11)
            - No. 4, 1987 (Box 12)
            - No. 5, 1988 (Box 12)
              - Miscellany, 1958, 1984-1986, undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)
              - Sejnowski, Terrence J., 1985-1986 (Box 12)
              - Text, 1987 (Box 12)
            - Nos. 6-7, (2 folders) (Box 12)
            - No. 8 (Box 12)
              - Apple Computers (Box 12)
              - Text, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 13)
            - No. 9, (2 folders) (Box 13)
        - No. 5, 1988 (Box 13)
        - “Corrected Copy,” undated (Box 13)
        - Fragments, 1987 (Box 13)
        - Martin, R. L., reader, 1988 (Box 14)
        - “Minds over Machines,” alternate title, drafts (Box 14)
          - No. 1, 1987-1988 (Box 14)
          - No. 2, chapters 1-9, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
          - Miscellany, undated (Box 14)
          - Penzias, David, reader, undated (Box 14)
        - Miscellany, undated, (1 folder) (Box 14, Box 15)
        - “The Syntax Matrix,” alternate title, drafts, 1985-1986 (Box 15)
          - No. 1, (4 folders) (Box 15)
          - No. 2, (1 folder); (3 folder) (Box 15, Box 16)
          - No. 3
      - Miscellany, 1989-1990, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Publication and promotion (Box 16)
        - Miscellany, 1988-1989 (Box 16)
        - Packets, 1989 (Box 16)
          - Jan.-Mar. (Box 16)
          - Apr.-May (Box 17)
        - Photographs and printed matter, 1989-1990 (Box 17)
        - Selma Shapiro Public Relations, 1988 (Box 17)
      - Research material, 1947, 1959, 1968-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
      - Reviews, 1988-1992 (Box 17)
      - Translations (Box 17)
        - Chinese, 1995 (Box 17)
        - French, 1989-1990, undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Poems, undated (Box 18)
  - Speeches and interviews (Box 18)
    - Development and writing, 1989-1995, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Events, 1979-2005, undated See also Oversize, (6 folders) (Box 19)
- Subject File, 1931-1998 (Box 19-27)
  Awards and honors, photographs, scientific papers, including research and articles, and other miscellaneous subject files.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Awards and honors (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1987, 1996 (Box 19)
    - New Jersey Literary Hall of Fame, 1991 (Box 19)
    - Nobel Prize for Physics See also Container 27, Notebook (Box 20)
      - Photographs, 1978 (Box 20)
        - “Day of Announcement” album, (2 folders) (Box 20)
        - Sweden (Box 20)
      - Proclamations and miscellaneous material, 1978 (Box 20)
      - Scrapbook, 1978, (4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Bell Laboratories and Lucent Technologies (Box 21)
    - Career file, 1983-1987, 1995 (Box 21)
    - Miscellany, 1981 (Box 21)
    - Poster, undated (Box 21)
    - Printed matter, 1979-1989, 1995-1998, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Retirement scrapbook, 1998, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Biography, family history, and early education (Box 21)
    - Brooklyn Technical High School, New York, N.Y. (Box 21)
      - Blueprint, yearbook, 1951 (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1951 (Box 21)
      - Student papers, 1948-1950 (Box 22)
    - College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y. (Box 22)
      - Miscellany, 1951-1954 (Box 22)
      - Student papers, 1950-1951 (Box 22)
    - Elementary, junior high, and Hebrew school, report cards, 1940-1946 (Box 22)
    - Germany, 1938-1939, 1979 (Box 22)
    - Miscellany, 1985 (Box 22)
  - Calendars, 1992-1998, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Commemorative “3K” T-shirt, 1978 See also Oversize (Box 22)
  - Controller-dispatcher, patent, 1994 (Box 22)
  - Levich, V. G. and Yeveny, case notebook, 1972-1974, (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Photographs (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 23)
    - Of Penzias, 1989, undated, (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - Printed matter, 1975, 1981, 1988, 1994-1995 (Box 23)
  - Reagan, Ronald, luncheon, 1985 (Box 23)
  - Science file (Box 23)
    - Deuterium in the universe (Box 23)
      - Articles (Box 23)
        - By Penzias (Box 23)
          - American Scientist, 1962, 1976-1977 (Box 23)
          - Miscellaneous, 1972-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 23)
        - By others, 1969-1978, undated, (5 folders) (Box 24)
      - International Astronomical Union, conference, Grenoble, France, 1976 (Box 24)
      - Miscellany, 1976 (Box 24)
    - Elements, origins of (Box 25)
      - Articles (Box 25)
        - By Penzias, 1972-1978 (Box 25)
        - By others, 1931, 1948-1949, 1957, 1965-1968, 1975-1978, (4 folders) (Box 25)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 25)
      - Lectures, undated (Box 25)
      - Miscellany, undated (Box 25)
    - Encrenaz, Pierre J., 1969-1974 (Box 25)
    - Horn Antenna, Holmdel, N.J., “chart record,” 1964 See Artifact (Box 26)
    - Isotope review file (Box 26)
      - Articles (Box 26)
        - By Penzias, 1973 (Box 26)
        - By others (Box 26)
          - Five College Radio Astronomy Observatory, Quabbin Reservoir, Mass., undated (Box 26)
          - Miscellaneous, 1969-1982, undated, (7 folders) (Box 26)
        - Notes, undated (Box 26)
    - Miscellany, undated (Box 27)
    - National Radio Astronomy Observatory, 1967-1975 (Box 27)
    - Notebook, 1978 See also Container 20, Nobel Prize, (4 folders) (Box 27)
- Oversize, 1978-1983 (Box OV 1-2)
  Commemorative T-shirt and posters.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Speeches and interviews (Box OV 1)
    - Events (Box OV 1)
      - Eighteenth Annual Karl G. Jansky Lecture, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va., poster, 1983 (Container 19) (Box OV 1)
  - Miscellany (Box OV 2)
    - Commemorative “3 K” T-shirt, 1978 (Container 22) (Box OV 2)
- Artifact, 1964 (Box VA 1)
  “Chart record,” Horn Antenna, Holmdel, N.J.
  Described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - “Chart record,” Horn Antenna, Holmdel, N.J., 1964 (Container 26) (Box VA 1)
- Digital Files, 1997-2006
  - Digital files, 1997-2006, mss85338_67_1_SIP